A Guide to the Papers of The Colson-Hill Family
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
A Guide to the Papers of The Colson-Hill Family 1833-1984
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1965-13
The Colson-Hill Papers are a gift of the Colson Family.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Beginnings of the Colson Family can be traced back to 1791. The Person of record was James Colson (1768-1824) who had been enslaved by a William Nelson of York County Virginia. He was emancipated in Williamsburg around 1791 and it is certain that by 1794 James Colson was living in Petersburg Virginia.
James Colson became a barber. This was one of the occupations free African American men were allowed to engage in. In 1804, Colson purchased a lot on Union Street and around 1820 another piece of property on Oak Street. James Colson died in 1825 and his son William took over the Business. In 1826 William Colson married Sarah Elebek. One of five children fathered by Major Elebek. Elebek like Colson was also a barber and a free African American.
William Colson became interested in the American Colonization Society's (1817-1895) efforts to remove to Africa all African Americans to what would become Liberia. At this time in Petersburg the Colson and Elebek families were members of the Methodist Church. Here they met another family by the name of Roberts. The Roberts and Colson family combined and formed a mercantile business, and Roberts and his family emigrated to Liberia. William Nelson Colson remained in Petersburg and managed the business from the U.S. side. In 1835 William Colson went to Liberia to confer with Roberts where he became ill and died.
Three children came from the Union of William and Sarah Elebek Colson. James Major, Mary Alexena and William Nelson Colson. Mary Alexena Colson married John K. Shore and William Nelson married Milvina and moved to Boston, Massachusetts. James Major Colson married Fannie Meade Bolling of Petersburg in 1850. Nine children were born to this couple.
The other component of this family were a mixture of free African American and enslaved family. John Henry Hill was born in King and Queen county Virginia in 1828. Like many others born into bondage, Hill was trained as a carpenter and was hired out by his owner. Although a native of King and Queen, Hill was either sold or rented out in Petersburg and in1853 was owned by a John Mitchell. Hill had also married a free African American woman, Rose McCray and they were the parents of two young sons.
Hill was enslaved and in 1853 his owner had decided to sell him. It is unclear how Hill found out. His possible sale and instead of being sold, he escaped. Hill found his way to Canada where his wife later joined him, and the seven Hill daughters were born. After the Civil War Hill returned to Petersburg, became a prosperous Businessman and engaged in local politics.
Edna Meade Colson was born October 7, 1888, in Petersburg, Virginia, the oldest of five children to James Major Colson, Jr., and his wife Kate Hill Colson who was one of the daughters of John Henry Hill.
Included in these materials is an interesting letter from William Still and in the Alice and Henry Colson Jackson Papers correspondence regarding the House of Roberts and Colson.
Edna Meade Colson was a product of the Petersburg public school system. After graduation from Peabody High School in 1904, she continued her education at Fisk University in Nashville, Tennessee. In 1908 she completed the Normal Course and joined the staff of Virginia State (then the Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute) in 1909. Edna Colson returned to Fisk and earned the Bachelor of Education in 1915. She later earned the Degrees of Bachelor of Science in 1923, Master of Arts in 1924, and Doctor of Philosophy in 1940 from Columbia Teachers College, New York. Her dissertation was An Analysis of Specific References to Negroes in Selected Curricula for the Education of Teachers.
During her career at Virginia State University Miss Colson served as classroom teacher, Supervisor of Student Teaching, Director of the Normal School, and Director of the Division of Education through the changing phases of the development of the University. In 1951 she became the Director of the newly created School of Education.
Miss Colson was very active in school functions at Teachers. She was Vice President of the Negro Education Club, and in 1931 she was a representative of the Club to the White House Conference on Education, and in the summer of 1939 she studied workshop organization at the University of Chicago.
Miss Colson was: affiliated with the American Association of University Professors, The Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, The Virginia Teachers Association, The Virginia Association of Jeanes Supervisors, and the Virginia Academy of Science, a life member of the American Teachers Association, a charter member of the Virginia Research Society, the National Association of College Women. The Virginia Interracial Commission, the Negro Organization Society, The American Red Cross, The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, a charter member of the Delta Omega Chapter of Alpha Kappa Alpha, and the Virginia State Federation of Colored Women's Clubs.
Miss Colson was a prolific writer and a highly sought after speaker throughout the state of Virginia. During her career she contributed articles to the Virginia State College Gazette, The Quarterly Journal of Higher Education for Negroes and the Journal of Negro Education.
Edna Colson was considered an authority on curriculum development and on source materials which could be used in teaching about the African American experience in America. She was considered by many to be the most influential person in the development of African American teachers, and teacher education.
Edna Colson corresponded with J.L. Blair, H.C. Newbold, L. C. Reynolds, Jannie Porter Barrett, A.G. Richardson, Eva Mitchell, Fred M. Alexander, D.A. Wilkerson, Rose Butler Brown, Mary Branch, Belle Boone Beard, and Mable Carney.
Scope and Content Information
The Colson Hill Family Papers document one of the most unique African-American families in the United States. This manuscript group covers this family's life and activities in the Commonwealth of Virginia from 1834-1984. These papers document the family's involvement with: The establishment of Liberia, the Underground Railroad, the establishment of Virginia State University, public education in Petersburg and in Virginia, the readjuster party, business in Petersburg and the social and community activities in the African American community as well. Not only did Miss Colson become keeper of the family papers, her long an outstanding career led to the creation of a large number of records documenting her productive life as well. Miss Colson was a teacher and a teacher of teachers. She was a student and believer in the idea that education could solve societies social, political, and economic ills. The papers provide a window into several aspects of African American society rarely scene. The bulk of the materials is in the form on correspondence, however, there are numerous printed items and photographs as well. The papers are quite useful for the study of: History of Education, Women's History, Local History, Family History, and Social and Economic History.
Series Description
Series I. History of the Colson Family Box # 1 Obituaries, records of birth, marriages and short sketches of members of the Colson-Hill Family
Sub-Series A. Family History A family history compiled by Alice A. Jackson for an exhibit about the Colson family. Included are copies of various documents and sketches of a number of family members.
Sub-Series B. Obituaries Funeral programs and several sketches of deceased family members.
Series II. Estate Correspodence and family documents Box #2 Legal documents covering various matters of the Colson-Hill family. This series includes Colson estate correspondence, wills, State and local tax receipts and leases for property Of special interest is an application for Canadian citizenship for John Henry Hill, who had escaped from the institution of slavery in 1857.
Series III. Family Correspondence, Telegrams and Postcards
Sub-Series A. Family Correspondence Boxes 3-15 Letters between members of this family for more than one hundred years. Subjects discussed, the underground railroad, family problems, education, politics, sound issues wars, politics and civil rights. The materials are arranged chronically Correspondence without dates are arranged by alphabet.
Sub-Series B. William Nelson Colson Boxes 16- A interesting number of letters written by William Nelson Colson (1890-1922) were found together and have been arranged accordingly. The materials include family correspondence, personal correspondence and correspondence pertaining to his days at Virginia Union University.
Sub-Series C: The Colson/Woody 1950-1967 Mainly correspondence having to do with Mary Colson's interest in the family estate. Included in this material is her will.
Sub-Series D: The John and Mary Colson Shore Papers 1844-1877 John K. Shore was married to Mary Colson and lived and worked in Petersburg. Shore was a barber, and after the Civil War served on the Common Council. The Shore papers consist mainly of tax and business receipts.
Sub-Series E: The John and Susie Hill Harris Papers 1900,1924 Papers of Susie Hill, sister of Kate Hill Colson. Photo, some correspondence.
Sub-Series F. Family Personal Box 20 Family correspondence with friends and associates. Very interesting letter from William Still to John Henry Hill.
Sub-Series G. Family Business Boxes 21-22 Records of family business activities from the anlebellum through the 1950's. Most of correspondece documents ownership and rents from family owned properties. Included in this sub-series are records of the House of Roberts and Colson (1833-1836) a merticle Company established by William Neslon Colson and Joseph Jenkins Roberts who became the first president of Liberia.
Sub-Series H. Family Work Box 23 James Major and Kate Hill Colsons work at the John A. Dix School in Dinwiddle County. John A. Dix was one of many little Tuskeeges established in the United States. Interesting Correspondence with and Colson work with the school improvement league. Series Includes records of the John A. Dix Industrial School.
Series IV. Edna Colson (Personal, Colson/Meredith, Education, Employment) 1905-1984
Sub-Series A. Correspondence Personal Box 24-28 Correspondence with friends and associates beginning in 1905 and continuting until 1980. This sub-series is arranged with Men Colson's correspondence maintained by date, and her correspondence kept by subject heading. Some of the correspondents, Ambrose Caliver, Gordan Hancock Jackson Davis, A.G. Richardson, and Carrie Gandy.
Sub-Series B. Colson/Meredith Correspondence Boxes 29-32 Correspondence between Edna Meade Colson and Amaza Meredith beginning in 1916 and continuing until 1982. Education, work, social and polilical and home ownership. The sub-series documents their vacation. Mister Colson and Meredith were companion for over fifty years.
Sub-Series C. Correspondence (Education) Box 33 Documents Ms.Colson's efforts to acquire graduated training during the era of segregation. Miss Colson's association with Teacher College began in 1924 and continued until 1964. Correspondence documents curriculum, research, problems faced by African American students encounted such as housing Colson's involvement with the Negro Education Club is also covered. The bulk of the correspondence is with Miss Mable Carney who was Edna Colson's major Professor at Columbia.
Sub-Series D. Correspondence (Employment) Box 34-47 Correspondence documenting Edna Meade Colson's forty-four years at Virginia State University. Arranged in there sections, correspondence with the presidents of Virginia State, by Subject heading and by alphabet. There are manuals of committees, information about public education in Virginia, reports. Arranged alphabetically and chronologically within the folder. Correspondence with John M. Gandy, Mable Carney, Luther Foster, Jackson Davis, Charles S. Johnson, and others.
Series V. Organizations and Affiliations of Edna Meade Colson Box # 48-60 This series contains material documenting Edna M. Colson's activities on and off the campus during her career at Virginia State University. Included in this series are records of: The Virginia Federation of Colored Women Clubs, the National Association of College Women, the Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority, the Chesterfield County "Colored" red Cross and others.
Sub-Series A. The Virginia Federation Of Colored Women's Clubs 1931,1961, Boxes 48-53 Records and Correspondence of the Petersburg Chapter of the Federation of Colored Women. Included are materials from the Petersburg Women's Council and the Virginia State College Education Club.
Sub-Series B. The National Association of College Women 1925-1964 Boxes 54-56 The National Association of Colored Women was organized in 1923 at Howard University. At this meeting a temporary NACW was established. One year later a larger group of African-American women met in Washington and formed a permanent "National Association of College Women." The Virginia State University Chapter was organized March 8th 1925 by Ms. Pauline Puryear. Edna Colson was one of the charter members. Mrs. Colson served as President of the Petersburg Branch, sectional director for the South and National Vice President. The materials include minutes, records, programs, photographs, and Correspondence.
Sub-Series C. Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority Inc. Boxes 57- 57 A, 57 B Correspondence, minutes and reports of the Delta Omega Graduate Chapter of Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority. Miss Colson was one of the charter members of this chapter, which was established at Virginia State University in 1925.
Sub-Series D. The Chesterfield County Red Cross 1929-1948 Box 58 Minutes, correspondence, reports and By-Laws of the Chesterfield County Red Cross. Miss Colson was the Chairman of the "Colored Auxiliary". The "Colored Auxiliary" attempted to ensure fair treatment in dispersing services being provided during the depression and the War years.
Sub-Series E. The Virginia Society for Research 1930-1934 Box 58 The Virginia Society for Research was established to promote and encourage serious research in the field of education, and to demonstrate that information derived from these efforts. Correspondence, minutes, and constitution.
Sub-Series F. The Negro Organizational Society 1912-1952 Box 59 The NOS was organized in 1912 to work on improving the schools, health, and homes of African American. This sub-series contains correspondence, reports and newsletters of this groups activities. Included in the materials are some correspondence concerning the School Improvement League.
Sub-Series G. The Gillfield Baptist Church 1910, 1974 Box 59 Correspondence, Parish Minister and information about placing stained glass windows in Gillfield.
Sub-Series H. The Links Incorporated 1958,1965 Container 59 Some materials about the Eastern Area Conference of the "Links Incorporated" one folder.
Sub-Series I. The Virginia Commission on Interracial Cooperation Box 59 One folder of correspondence
Sub-Series J. The Committee for Virginia 1940,1946 Box 59 One folder, includes a Constitution written in 1940 and some correspondence
Sub-Series K. The N.A.A.C.P 1949 Two folders, Correspondence to Edna Colson about membership. One Folder contains a copy of a Petersburg Chapter Newsletters.
Sub-Series L The Virginia Council On Human Relations 1955-1975 Box 60 Correspondence, Reports, minutes, and printed items. The correspondence and addresses a number of social and political issues which were of great concern during this time. Miss Colson was a member of the board of Directors.
Sub-Series M. The Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee 1960 Box 60 Newsletters and hand-bills
Sub-Series N. The SCLC 1961-1964 Box 60 SCLC Newsletter 1961, 1966
Series VI. Literary Box # 61-63 Diaries, speeches and articles produced by family members. In this series are a number of diaries of James Major Colson. While he was a student at Dartmouth College. The majority of the materials however are writings and speeches of Edna M. Colson.
Series VII. Financial Records Boxes # 64-66 Receipts and bills for school, rental household (including furniture, food, and clothing). There are a number of ledgers.
Sub-Series A. Receipts and Bills Boxes # 64-65 A unique array of receipts and bills of the Colson-Hill Family. Included are receipts for rent, school bills, medical receipts, household (including furniture, food, and clothing), and contractors.
Sub-Series B. Ledgers and Bank Books Box # 66 Rental books maintained by the Colson-Hill family. The Ledgers also contain information about family purchases and receipts for building and contractors.
Series VIII. Photographs Boxes 67-74 Photographs of family and friends. The material is arranged into several sub-series.
Sub-Series A. Family ,Many of the photos in these paper were taken on the 1870's and 80's.
Sub-Series B. William Nelson Colson III. Colson, was a student studying law at Harvard University in 1917 when he decided to join the United State Army. The photo's which William Nelson sent home from Fort Ames,Iowa gave his family and friends some idea of what he was doing in officers training school. The photos incude some postcards of camp scenes.
Sub-series C. Photographs- Friends(by name), of Edna Meade Colson or school affiliations. In addition there are a number of photographs of individuals,quit a few were friends or former students of Kate Colson. Many of the photographs are not identified by name. Many of the photographs were taken in the following locations: The Leath Company, Rockwell and the New York Gallery were all in Petersburg others were taken in Richmond, Danville, New York, Winston-Salem, Baltimore, Philadelphia and Washington D.C.
Sub-Series D. Photograph Book Photo Book containing mostly tin-types of friends of the Colson-Hill family. Most are in color.
Series IX. Scrapbooks Twelve scrapbooks generated by Edna Meade Colson. Each book is titled. Most of the books consist of photo's some correspondence, news-clippings and postcards.
Series X. Printed
Sub-Series A. Programs, Invitations, Pamphlets Programs, Invitations, and Pamphlets collected by family members.
Sub-Series B. Degrees Grade reports for several members of the Colson family. Of particular interest James Major Colson Jr's prep school reports.
Sub-Series C. Newspaper Clippings News clippings of particular interest to members of the family.
Contents List
- History of the Colson family
  - Family History
    - Family History-J.M. Colson- Biographical Sketch (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Family History-Family Sketches (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Family History- William Nelson Colson (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Family History- The Colson Family of Petersburg (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Family History- Family Birth Record (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Family History- Geneology (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Obituaries
    - Family History- John Hill's death (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Family History- Obituaries, Births, and Deaths (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Family History- Colson Obituary (Box-folder 1:9)
- Legal Documents
  - Estate Correspondence
    - Legal- Colson Estate Correspondence 1891-1950 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Legal- Colson Estate (Mrs. W.N.Colson) 1926-1929 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Legal- Colson Estate 1910 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Family Documents
    - "Will" 1928 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Legal- Colson passport copy 1838 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Legal- Application for Canadian Citizenship 1857 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Legal- Deed (Petersburg) 1859 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Legal- Deed (Petersburg- Shore St.) 1888 (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Legal- Deed (Petersburg- Bryne St.) 1925 (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Legal- Deed (New St.) 1950 (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Legal- Indenture 1885 (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Legal- Easment-Azurest 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Legal- Article of agreement 1872 (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Legal- Teaching Contracts 1881,1884,1891 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Legal- Teaching Contracts V.N. and I.I 1921,1923,1925,1927 (Box-folder 2:15)
    - Legal- Plat Maps 1906 (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Legal- Power of Attorney 1928 (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Legal- State tax Receipts 1891-1917 (Box-folder 2:18)
    - Legal- State Tax Receipts 1918-1922 (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Legal- State Tax Receipts 1923-1926 (Box-folder 2:20)
    - Legal- City Tax Reciepts( Petersburg) 1908-10,1957 (Box-folder 2:21)
    - Legal- City tax Receipts (Petersburg) 1911-1914 (Box-folder 2:22)
    - Legal- City tax Reciepts (Petersburg) 1915,1920-22 (Box-folder 2:23)
    - Legal- City Tax Receipts 1923-1927 (Box-folder 2:24)
    - Legal- Tax Receipts (Prince George Co.) 1908 (Box-folder 2A:1)
    - Legal- Lease (Box-folder 2A:2)
    - Legal- Leases- Sycamore Street (Box-folder 2A:3)
    - Legal- School Receipts and Bills (Box-folder 2A:4)
    - School- Transcripts 1910 (Box-folder 2A:5)
    - Legal- Transcript (Peabody) (Box-folder 2A:6)
    - Legal- Stocks and Bonds (Box-folder 2A:7)
    - Insurance Policies (Box-folder 2A:8)
    - Endowment the right Worthy Grand Council- Independent Order of St.Luke- 1905-O.S 1905 (Box-folder 2A:9)
    - The Richmond Beneficial Insurance Co- 1911 (matted) O.S. 1911 (Box-folder 2A:10)
    - The Grand Fountain of the United Order of the True Reformers- 1901- O.S 1901 (Box-folder 2A:11)
- Family Correspondence, Telegrams,and Postcards-1845,1866-1980 1845,1866-1980
  - Family Correspondence
    - Family Correspondence 1845,1866 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Family Correspondence 1866-1868 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Family Correspondence 1882-1883 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Courtship Correspondence 1883-1885 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Family Correspondence 1884-1885 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Family Correspondence 1887-88,1890 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Family Correspondence 1893-1894 (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Family Correspondence 1896-1897 (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Family Correspondence Jun 4-15 1898 (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Family Correspondence Jun 16-30 1898 (Box-folder 3:10)
    - Family Correspondence Jul 3-17 1898 (Box-folder 3:11)
    - Family Correspondence Jul 7-19 1898 (Box-folder 3:12)
    - Family Correspondence 1899 (Box-folder 3:13)
    - Family Correspondence 1901-1903 (Box-folder 3:14)
    - Family Correspondence 1904 (Box-folder 3:15)
    - Family Correspondence 1907 (Box-folder 3:16)
    - Family Correspondence Jan-Mar 1908 (Box-folder 4:1)
    - Family Correspondence Apr- Sept 1908 (Box-folder 4:2)
    - Family Correspondence Oct-Dec 1908 (Box-folder 4:3)
    - Family Correspondence Jan-Jun (Box-folder 4:4)
    - Family Correspondence Jul-Dec 1909 (Box-folder 4:5)
    - Family Correspondence- The Death of J.M. Colson May 22-26 (Box-folder 4:6)
    - Family Correspondence Jun-Aug 1909 (Box-folder 4:7)
    - Family Correspondence May 1910 (Box-folder 4:8)
    - Family Correspondence June 1910 (Box-folder 4:9)
    - Family Correspondence May 1911 (Box-folder 4:10)
    - Family Correspondence Dec 1911 (Box-folder 4:11)
    - Family Correspondence Jan-Feb 1912 (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Family Correspondence Mar-Jun 1912 (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Family Correspondence Aug-Dec 1912 (Box-folder 5:3)
    - Family Correspondence Jan-Feb 1913 (Box-folder 5:4)
    - Family Correspondence Mar-Apr 1913 (Box-folder 5:5)
    - Family Correspondence May 1913 (Box-folder 5:6)
    - Family Correspondence Sept-Dec 1913 (Box-folder 5:7)
    - Family Correspondence Jan-Apr 1914 (Box-folder 5:8)
    - Family Correspondence May-Dec 1914 (Box-folder 5:9)